OK, let's get us started.
Good afternoon.
Welcome back to another lecture in digital design, computer Architecture.
Today we're going to continue what we have started about pipelining yesterday and hopefully we're
going to be able to finish pipelining today, next week on Thursday, we're going to continue in the
some other topics related to pipelining and also out of order execution which we're going to see I
guess after Easter break.
So essentially we will try to finish pipelining and issues in pipelining mostly the control and data
dependence handling today.
And regarding state maintenance and recovery which is the topic of precise exception, we're going to
see much more next week and hopefully after Easter break we're going to also see out of order
execution.
So here are our readings which we have used them for last week and also today.
So you can also check them.
Actually H&H is a very good, there are a lot of good chapters related to these topics.
So for multi cycle, I would really recommend you check HNH and the pattern pattern.
Also I showed some of the slides related to that, especially about the micro micro program
controller design.
OK, So we've seen single cycle micro architecture and also we build a better architecture more let's
say principle design.
We build multi cycle MIPS processor and then we actually mentioned that in the multi cycle MIPS
processor we can easily handle multi cycle memory accesses.
We essentially wait in some of the states until we get to the until the memory is ready and then we
ask this question, can we do better?
And then we get to this pipelining.
This was the slide that we were kind of through the end of the lecture yesterday and we were showing
some example about four independent additions like add instructions.
So in multi cycle this addition will take 4 cycles per instruction.
So you you fetch the code, execute and do write back and then after that you go to the next
instruction, the next and the next.
But in the pipeline design, you actually while you are decoding the first instruction, you can fetch
the second.
And while you are executing the first instruction, you can decode the second instruction and fetch
the third instruction.
And after some time when your pipeline is full, you can actually have this throughput of 1
instruction per cycle.
So in the city state, which means the, the, the position that your pipeline is full, are you going
to have the throughput of 1 instruction completed everyone cycle?
But essentially we need to ask this question that is life always this beautiful, which we're going
to see that in pipelining, there are a lot of heats which cause us not getting to this beautiful
life.
And we need to design techniques how to, to overcome these are these limitations.
I'm going to quickly also go over this laundry analogy, which might be interesting also for you in
the pipelining, because actually pipelining is a topic that we are observing it in our real life
everyday.
So in a laundry analogy, for example, you need to you have some clothes, dirty clothes and you want
to wash them and then you need to put them in the dryer.
And then you basically fold your clothes and then put your put the clothes in the in the clothes.
So in kind of a multi cycle, let's say laundry, you essentially so you don't overlap things, right?
You wash and dry fold and then put the closet and then go to the next load of your clothes.
So in this example, we know that steps to do a load in this case like dirty load for laundry, like
laundry load, they are sequentially essentially dependent.
However, no dependence between different loads.
So these loads that we have for example for the B sequence in task order is actually independent of
the of the task order.
A also different steps do not require the same resources.
So when you do washing, you don't need to do anything with the dryer essentially.
So these are very important thing about this analogy which we're going to see also later on when we
are designing pipelining.
So you can actually pipeline this design by that once you are doing the washing for the for the
first task.
A, you can actually also do the, sorry, when you're drawing task order A, you can wash the start
washing task or task B and so on and so forth.
So with that, you can actually provide better throughput.
So now we can have 4 loads of laundry in parallel in a steady state when the pipeline is full.
And essentially our throughput increased by 4 times if you check the timing as well.
However, I should also mention that latency per load is the same.
Actually this was the case also in our previous example here that each single instruction would
still take 4 cycles.
Here actually cycle time can be different from pipeline design and multi cycle.
So we did with that in mind.
And actually this cycle time might be might not be too off, but they are also different when you
have a pipeline processor and multi cycle processor, but also, but the number of cycles is still
the same.
So for the every single instruction, so every single instruction you need to spend 4 cycles to
finish.
But overall your throughput is going to be better because you're because you're benefiting from this
concurrency that in the steady state you can finish one instruction per cycle.
OK.
So yeah.
But so in a more realistic pipelining in for laundry load your dryer, which I think you guys can
agree also because the dryer always takes longer time is is that's the case actually also in my
apartment as well.
So essentially that would limit the throughput of your pipeline design.
So here in in a non pipeline design you can finish one load every 150 minutes because of the slow
dryer when you want to actually pipeline it.
So this slow dryer would not let you to start actually the basically you need to wait until this
slow so you can start washing the, the task B, but you cannot do the drying of that because this
dryer would take longer time.
So you need to essentially wait longer.
So if you calculate the timing, you're going to see that this is going to be 1 load every 60 minutes
because of this slow dryer.
So the slowest step, which in this example is a dryer actually decides the throughput for us.
So how can we overcome that?
There are multiple ways of it in this example in this context as well.
One way would be that we we buy a second dryer.
When you are doing this task order for task A, you use the dryer A, when you want to do this task B,
you use dryer B.
And essentially you alternate between A&B in order to essentially finish your pipeline faster.
So with this example, you can finish essentially you can have one load every 30 minutes, which
again, we can get back to our 4/4 times higher throughput.
You can also think of some techniques to have to have faster dryers as well.
So I mean, I'm, I'm using this analogy to give you also some concept concepts in also designing
micro architecture.
So whenever we have some slow, let's say units, like for example, multiplayer for us is much slower.
You can think of, I would add several multipliers in this in in the ALU for example, or you can
think of using some algorithms in order to make multiplayer faster and that can provide you better
throughput in your pipeline in design.
Here is also another analogy just for fun.
This actually a real life pipeline automobile assembly which there was a actually interesting unit
has been developed.
This Magneto which has been used for provide the energy for ignition in basically for Ford
automobile and in in the I mean you can actually clearly read that.
But so before actually having the pipeline assembly there you have this on average that worker could
assemble 35 of these Magneto in a nine hour shift or roughly one every 15 minutes.
And then then essentially after some time for the transmission to moving assembly lines, which
happened in 1913.
So then they get to this essentially the throughput of assembly time from about 15 minutes to 5 S 3
times faster basically speed up in generation of this magnet.
Also, if you want to, if you're if you're familiar with this X-Men, you can also you might know
about.
Magneto in that context as well.
So you can also check if you're interested and think about the analogy between that Magneto and also
Ford Magneto.
And this is actually much more modern automobile assembly that we have today, which is important in
order to provide throughput.
And pipeline is actually very old topic and this is actually one of the an old pipeline computer in
IBM stretch, which actually you can see that it's kind of quite huge, like the weight of it is
actually 35 tones, something like that, which is quite heavy and also quite expensive.
But this idea of pipelining has been used for a long time.
So essentially I want to say that pipelining is actually a real technique and people have been using
it for in different contexts, not only in micro architecture.
And so, so now let's get to some definition of ideal pipeline.
So our goal is to increase increase the throughput with little increase in cost, which that cost can
be hardware cost in case of instruction processing.
And in order to get that we want to we, we need some assumptions or let's say some requirements.
First of all, we need the repetition of identical operations.
So we want to have same operation is repeated on a large number of different inputs.
So in our example, all laundry loads go through the same steps like washing dryer and folding and
also putting to the closet.
If you have some instructions or some operations that may not go over all these steps, then you have
some problems in your pipeline design.
Also reputation of independent operation is also important.
So we want these operations be independent of.
So in our laundry example, different loads are completely independent so they don't need to wait for
each other to finish.
So no dependences between repeated operations.
Is also very important to have have an ideal pipeline.
Also we want to have uniformly partitionable sub operations, so processing can be evenly divided
into uniform latency sub sub operations.
So in our laundry example, for example, we've seen that a dryer can take longer time.
So if that's the case, then you don't really have this uniformly distributed uniformly partitionable
sub operations.
So that's also very important such that you can break your latency into same latencies, which which
is important for better pipelining design.
We're going to see examples about that also very soon.
OK, so automobile assembly line or doing laundry is actually a very good fitting example, but we
want to see this context is actually an instruction processing cycle.
So this is for, you know, kind of a design that you can think of is actually you can think of as a
single cycle design because you have some registers and then you need to do some combinational
logic in your combinational logic can be actually all these fetch, decode, execute memory and write
back, which going to take like T picoseconds.
And then the output, you're going to write it back to the to some registers, you know, so that
register can be the same register as here or can be different registers.
So once you have this kind of a design, your throughput is actually 1 / t This is the throughput
that you're getting from this system.
So you can actually break this combination logic into two and then add another state register in
between.
So with that you can actually have a throughput of 2 / t So you you can hopefully expect that you
are maximum you're increasing throughput by two by 2X.
You can also break it to three and then potentially you can increase the throughput by 3X.
But this is actually we are assuming here that this T picosecond is actually partitionable in two
perfectly and then you can perfectly partition this T to three stages and so on and so forth.
So that's actually one of the assumption here in this example that we are getting to this ideal
pipeline, a more realistic pipeline throughput is that you essentially you need to also consider
this sequencing delay which you know from our timing lecture whenever we want to write to the
registers, we need to deal with the whole time and set up time, right, which we discussed about it
as a sequencing overhead.
So the throughput of this system which is kind of a single cycle design is actually 1 / T + S and T
is a combination of delay and S is actually the delay we need to spend for this sequencing
overhead.
So once you actually have your pipeline with KS stage, assuming that you can actually perfectly
partition your tasks.
Into K stages.
So your latency of combinational logic is actually coming t / K, but then you still need to pay the
overhead of S.
So the throughput is going to be 1 / t / K + s.
So when, when K actually goes to Infinity, this t / K is going to be 0 or for example, let's say 1
gate delay.
And then you're going to have this sequencing overhead, which that's going to be your essentially
your limiting throughput in the end.
So in the end, as the more you increase your stages, at some point, the the useful operation that
you're doing per stage is going to be very, very little.
And then you are just paying the overhead only for sequencing the for the registers, which is not a
very good and wise thoughtful design.
So theoretically if you don't have that sequencing overhead, you really want to increase the the
number of stages, but that sequencing overhead at some point comes to play and that would limit
your performance.
There are also many other reasons that we're going to also see today that we don't we, we may not
be, we may not prefer to increase the the number of stage stages of the pipeline to to infinite
number.
So there should be actually control on that.
Also we're going to see a bit more.
OK.
So register delay reduces throughput which is sequencing overhead between the stages.
And still this picture assumes perfect division of work between the stages which we are already
discussed, OK.
Also regarding the cost, so here for example, you have G gates in your single cycle design and also
you have this the cost for the register which is R.
So in in this design is G + R Once you have it, the K stage pipeline, then again assuming that you
can perfectly partition in each of your combinational circuit, you're going to have G / K gates and
then you have essentially K registers.
So the the cost is going to be again G+ RK.
So then at some point actually by increasing the number of stages, this G is not going to change,
which in reality would also change.
But then you're going to the cost is going to increase because of adding registers.
So in the end register increase the hardware costs.
So that should be also considered to not have too many, let's say, pipeline stages.
OK, any question?
OK, so now let's get to see how we can do this pipeline instruction processing for our fetch,
decode, evaluate, address, fetch operands, execute and store.
So remember that we had these steps instruction fetch, instruction decode and register for access,
execute and address generation memory and also write back steps.
So we started with a single cycle micro architecture.
And we actually this one of the reason that we started a single cycle actually was that to say that
it's a bad idea.
So it's good to actually.
Show also bad ideas that people have developed for for the for educational perspective.
But single cycle micro architecture is actually also useful when you want to design pipeline design.
So you can come up with a single cycle micro architecture and then you can add pipeline registers in
between of the stages.
And that can actually can be a very nice shortcut when you want to design A pipeline system.
So that's why now we are getting back to our single cycle micro micro architecture.
And so this actually part of the data pass in our single cycle micro architecture is not complete.
But overall we get to this design when we are designing single cycle micro architecture.
And then you you can have different latencies for these stages.
So assuming that instruction fetch is 200 picosecond, decode is 100 picosecond, execute is also 200,
memory is also 200 and then write back is 100 picosecond.
And you need to somehow add some registers in between of these stages to make a pipeline.
But we want to say first get to this some analysis how much performance we are getting from such
system.
And also there are some, you know feedback that essentially these wires are going back to some of
the earlier stages and there's going to be actually problematic when we want to design the
pipeline.
We're going to get to that also later, but ignore for now for simplicity.
OK, so one question is that is this the correct partitioning?
So of course we can see that there are some stages that essentially the the latency is much lower
than 200 because again.
Half of it.
So that actually can rings the bell here that it may not be the perfect partitioning because in the
perfect partitioning we want to have equally latencies for all the stages.
But at some point also it's not easy to do that.
So we should also consider that life is not that beautiful all the time.
And so in the end, we might get to some pipeline that we have different latencies among the stages.
Hopefully we're going to have, we should try to have balance latency as much as possible like in
some order, but it might not be the case that they are perfectly equal.
So that's one thing.
But then also people can ask why not four or six stages because here we have 5 stages and this can
be actually with different evaluation.
So in the end, how many stages we need to come up and how we need to how we're going to break the
pipeline to different stages.
That's actually is a is a big design decisions which needs actually a lot of evaluation in the end
by adding some stages, because by adding a stages, you might have a better clock cycle.
But then there are some drawbacks of the pipelining, which can actually cause more issues when you
when you have a deeper pipeline.
So we're going to see that some of them in the later part of this lecture.
But just note that this actually is not a easy question to answer and a lot of design decision in
going on when we are when people are designing pipelines.
OK, so in this essentially example, assuming you have load word instructions, so in a single cycle
way, you need to do instruction fetch, register access, ALU data access and then write back.
So this going to take 800 picosecond and then after that, we're going to get to the next
instruction, next index.
But in our pipeline design, we can do instruction fetch for 200 picosecond.
And then this state actually even though register can be accessed in 100 picosecond, but we cannot
have a different clock cycle, right?
So you need to actually wait for 200 picosecond for register, for register file access, and also for
this write back.
Even though you can do it in 100 picosecond, you still need to wait for 200 picoseconds.
So in the steady state, assuming that you're going to execute all, I mean load words for the
infinite amount of time.
So this pipeline is going to be full at some point and then you're going to have one instruction
meaning that one load per every 200 picosecond.
So you're going to get to the speed up of four.
So it's 5A stage of speed up.
Basically five stage pipeline gives us speed up 4 which is not 5.
So that you can see that when your pipeline is not perfectly partitioned, you may not get to that
ideal speed up that you were looking at.
But actually 4 is pretty good speed up for this five stage pipeline as well.
OK.
So when we when we want to enable pipeline processing, we need to apply add pipeline registers.
So in this example, essentially we need to add some registers here.
This one is used for let's say instruction fetch and decode.
So essentially the instruction that you're fetching here, you need to store it in this pipeline
register and then you feed it to the next cycle to the for the decoded state.
And there are going to be also another Register here pipeline, which is for instruction decode and
execute and another pipeline Register here, which is for execute and memory.
So output of the previous stage and input of the the next stage and also another pipeline register
which is for memory and write back.
So here I think there is something important that we need to think about it as of now that different
instructions are actually running in this design.
So in this pipeline design.
So once you fetch 1 instruction and then you when you get to this decoding of this instruction in
this state, actually there is another instruction here which doing fetch for that.
And when you are doing execute of 1 instruction, there is another instruction here which you are
doing decoding of it and also another instruction here that you are doing fetch order.
So this is actually very important and that's help is important that how we design these registers
and how we control our control signals in this design.
So we're going to see that, OK, So for example, PCPC plus 4 you generate in this stage and then you
also provide the instruction from the instruction memory.
So you put it in this pipeline register such that you can move it to the to the next stage.
And also PC +4 that you calculated here you also need to put it in this register and to move it to
the next stage because.
The PC Plus 4, which going to be in the next cycle is actually different.
So you cannot always in a single cycle design.
You have your PC +4 and you can use it for all the stages, right?
But in pipeline, the PC +4 that you generate for this instruction A, you need to move it to your
pipeline such that in the later stages while you're executing instruction A, you have your PC +4.
Yes.
Exactly.
Yeah, yeah.
So, yeah, you're look, you're actually thinking a bit ahead of time which is very good.
And that's actually called control dependence which we're going to see later today how we handle
essentially we need to you need to have some technique to flush the pipeline for those instructions
that you have fetched wrongly essentially.
So we're going to see that.
But very good thing that you're actually, it's good to think about the problems of how when we
design pipelines, at some point you are not able to actually move all these instructions also
back-to-back because some of these instructions are dependent.
Like for example, there might be some instructions that while you're accessing the register file.
So the the read register that this instruction is, is actually going to be updated by a older
instruction which is already here.
So you don't have the updated value essentially your register file because that's going to be happen
after the write back.
So that younger instruction may actually fetch an absolute value of that register.
So these are actually very important things to think about it here and we're going to see how we can
handle that in such a design.
OK, so that's essentially you need to add this pipeline registers and everything needed for the
later stages you need to actually put in these registers.
So we need actually PC Plus 4 here as well because in your in order to calculate the the target
address for branch instructions, you need to have PC +4.
So essentially and you're doing it in this stage.
So you need to actually also pass PC +4 to the next stage and then to the next here such that you
can calculate.
And after here when we calculate the new PC, we again need to put it in the pipeline register which
going to be used to update the PC.
So that's about the data values.
Another thing in this kind of a pipeline design, which is a kind of a linear traditional pipeline.
So all instruction classes must follow the same paths and timing through the pipeline stages.
So load word essentially is a good example because load word actually needs to go over all these
stages like fetch, decode, execute for address generation and then accessing the memory and then
writing back.
However, another instruction you can think of subtract which you fit to the pipeline after the load
word.
So this subtract also needs to go over all these stages even though subtract has nothing to do in
the memory stage.
But for this way of designing pipeline, which is a kind of very traditional way of pipeline design
that subtract instruction also needs to go over all these stages.
We're going to see later in other pipeline design in also in other order execution that that doesn't
need to be always the case.
So you can actually have a different design.
But in this linear pipeline essentially you consider that all the instructions actually will go
through all these steps, which makes the design much easier.
OK.
So again, we are asking this that his life always is beautiful, which actually here we are
considering that this subtract, you know, all the registers that this subtract is using to load
this dollar register 2 and register three, they are not, they are not changed by the load work.
But for example, if this subtract has to read register 10, then you had to have you have a problem
which we're going to see how about it later.
So in operation view, you can also have it in this kind of a chart.
Whenever you want to judge about the performance of the pipeline design, you have different
instruction and they need to go over this fresh decode execute memory.
And right back and at some point your pipeline is full and assuming that you have, let's say too
many of these instructions, your pipeline will stay full for some time and then you're going to
have a very good throughput.
You can also think of as it in a resource view in this kind of a table which you have different
stages of the pipeline and also different cycles.
So in this table you can see how these instructions are moving through the through these steps
So after some time the steady state every cycle you are doing full useful works essentially.
OK, so now we know about datapaths in the pipeline design.
What should we do for the control in the pipeline design?
So the good thing here is that the control signals, they are actually identical set of control as we
designed in the single cycle micro architecture.
So all the control signals that we have had in the single cycle micro architecture, they're going to
be also here useful for pipeline design.
There is only one difference here that in single cycle you fetch the instruction and then you
generate the control signals and all these control signals going to be used at the same cycle,
right.
However, in the pipeline design, these control signals are going to be used in different cycles.
So still we have the same set of let's say control signals which you're going to use, but then it's
going to be different because at the different cycles they're going to be different.
So control signal require different cycle depending on the stage.
So we have two options how we want to deal with that.
One option is that now we decode once using the same logic as a single cycle micro architecture.
So once you fetch your instruction, you decode the instruction, you generate the control signals,
and then you essentially buffer these control signals until consumed.
So which is actually depicted in this picture.
So you generate the control signals and then you need to make your pipeline resistors bigger.
So the control signals that they need to be used for later stages, you essentially send it to this
pipeline register.
So you pipeline them and then send it back to the send it to the next stage and the next stage until
they are consumed.
So essentially here, which is the execute stage.
So this control signals that they are used for the executed stage are going to be consumed and then
that's why you don't feed it to the to the next stage.
However, the the control signals for the memory stage are going to actually just sent to the next
stage and then in this stage they're going to be consumed and then you're done and you only have
your write back control signals.
So that's one way of designing control in a pipeline design.
Another option is that we carry relevant instruction board or field.
So part of the instruction that they're relevant for generating control signal, you can actually
carry that down the pipeline and decode locally.
So then you're going to actually have a distributed decoding logic which so essentially in every
step you do some decoding locally.
So of course here there is a trade off and different design have used different part of this
actually these options.
But in this course actually we're going to consider the option one in this lecture at least.
So, yeah, so essentially here you can see that in this picture as well in our pipeline design that
these are the pipeline registers.
And then we also add the some to these register in order to have these control signals pipelined
essentially.
OK.
So yeah, so essentially the the right back control is going to be used at the at the very, very
last, this Reg right register file enable.
So that's why you need to carry it to all the stages.
And then in the end, you're going to use it.
OK.
And here is also the pipeline design in your book, which actually they did a pretty good job.
So I, I recommend everyone also check the book for for better understanding, even though in this
lecture we're going to actually explain all the important topics about it, but you can also check
For more information if you're interested.
So, so here in this example of the book, saying that essentially the the value that you want to
write to the register file is generated in this stage.
And then we moved this, sorry, the, the, the address.
This is the address, yes the destination register, which you want to write in the register file.
Is generated here and then we are moving it to the through this, you know, feedback to the register
for and actually the your book is asking that is this correct?
Which I think you can say quickly, is this correct?
Yes, yes.
And why?
Because at that point we're trying to write the register, but that instruction hasn't finished
exactly.
And actually there is another instruction.
There is actually another instruction here which is completely different.
So you, you need to exactly, you need to 1st finish that instruction and then in the right back mode
when you really have your data ready and then you need to provide that address.
So that's why in your book also say that yeah, essentially you need to send this address to the next
stage of the pipeline and then move it to the next stage of the pipeline.
And in the right backstage you essentially provide this address to the register file.
So yeah, that's more or less what we need to think about it when we are designing the pipeline
system.
Any question?
machine we built last time?
Well, in in multi cycle for example machine, we consider that we have a instruction data memory.
Remember that in order to reduce the cost, we say that we can have one memory which is used for
instruction fetch and also data memory.
But here, for example, in order to avoid resource dependence, like for example, when, when, when one
instruction is fetching is getting fetched, there might be some other instructions that we are
accessing the memory and they are writing to the memory.
So then you need to actually have different memory for a better pipeline design.
So that's why actually this architecture is more or less similar to the single cycle micro
architecture.
You know, if you just remove these pipeline registers, you're going to see that it's actually very
much similar to the single cycle micro architecture.
But the idea is the same.
Still we are doing in multi cycle, but multi cycle in a in a sense that every cycle there are
multiple instructions in the in the in the pipeline that they are executing.
So in each cycle you are executing part of the instruction, which is similar in that sense with a
multi cycle design, but there are multiple instructions in this, in this case now.
Yeah.
Can we somehow combine this pipeline with multi cycles?
Yes, it is possible.
And we're going to see actually there is a nice combination.
We're going to see it later I guess maybe next week or maybe after Easter break.
Yeah, this is a very good question actually.
Any other question?
OK, so and it's actually also another example of pipeline control that you can see that this control
unit generates control signals and then we.
Essentially move them to to this pipeline resistors.
OK, so when we want to design A pipeline processor, it's also not much different from the single
cycle or multi cycle the way that we design.
So we first come up with the data pass and then we need to design the control logic.
However, basically what we discussed here is that in a pipeline data pass design, you can actually
start with a single cycle data pass and decide how to break it down into stages.
And then we add pipeline registers to separate stages from each other.
We propagate data signals to stages where they are needed and we make sure correct action is done in
in the correct stage.
So those wires that they cross stages need to be handled carefully like some of these control
signals, some of these like also the the address for the destination register.
So these are actually problematic wires which you need to handle it carefully.
Also for the pipeline control logic, we start with the single cycle control signals and control
logic and then we propagate each control signal to stages where it is needed.
OK, so that's a summary of what we have done so far.
But now the question is that is this sufficient?
And we're going to see a lot now in that line like how do we handle dependent instructions?
As also I showed you quickly, some of these instructions that they are moving back-to-back, they
might be dependent on each other.
So you cannot really keep executing them.
So we're going to see that and how do we handle multi cycle memory access?
So there might be some.
So in your load instruction you might be stuck in your memory.
For a long time.
So how are you going to handle it essentially?
And also one of your colleagues actually talked about branch instructions which can actually cause a
lot of problems.
We're going to hopefully get to that as so remember an ideal pipeline that we discussed, we want to
have a repetition of identical operations, repetition of independent operation and uniformly,
uniformly partitionable sub operations.
So now let's look at essentially our instruction pipeline and unfortunately none of them is actually
there.
So it's very hard to get ideal pipeline when we are designing microprocessor.
So first of all, identical operations, clearly no, because we have different instructions that not
all need the same stages.
So that basically we, we are forcing all instructions to go through the same pipeline stages which
might not be really good for performance reasons and also for energy reasons.
So that's actually called external fragmentation.
So some pipeline stages idle for some instructions.
Another problem is that we we don't have uniform sub sub operations.
So different pipeline stations, they do not have the same latencies which is called internal
fragmentation.
And another problem is that we have we don't, we might not not have independent operations.
So instructions are in reality they might be independent, might be actually dependent on each other.
Some of these instructions are actually are kind of a producer and consumer.
So your, your instruction, your early instructions are producing some value and this value needs to
be consumed by later, later instructions.
So clearly you have the data dependence here, which you need to handle it somehow.
And also you have control dependence because of branch instructions.
So these are actually very important.
And we, we, you need to actually handle them, handle them nicely in order to have a correct
execution in your pipeline.
So now the question actually in the end is that how we design A correct pipeline that can handle all
these dependencies and problems while you're actually maximising performance.
So in the end that's the designer, you know the goal to achieve.
So we are not going to design A pipeline which is not correct.
So that's of course the the important, the most important thing.
But we also want to have a high performance pipeline as we optimise the system.
So essentially for this independent for dependence of the operation, we need to detect and resolve
inter instruction dependencies to ensure the pipeline provides correct results.
So detecting of them and resolving is very important.
So one important concept here is actually pipeline stalls.
So at some point you cannot keep moving your pipeline and you need to stall your pipeline in order
to make sure that your pipeline is correct.
So we're going to get to that also very soon.
So in pipeline, actually balancing working pipeline stages is very hard.
And this has been a problem and still also I mean it's very hard thing to do like how many stages
and what is done in each stage.
So today's processor actually if you check they have very different number of stages, some of them
they have 10s they some of them they have 1520.
So there are many different number of stages.
There are also some specialised processor that they might have much deeper pipeline like 10s of
pipeline stages.
But essentially this is very important and one of the hard decision making for one of the hardest,
hardest decision for the the designers.
Another important is that basically we keeping the pipeline correct, moving and full.
So correct of course is important.
However, moving and full is also very important in order to provide performance improvement in the
presence of events that disrupt pipeline flow.
So there are different reasons handling dependencies, data dependencies and also control
dependencies, which you're going to see that and also handling resource contention.
So sometimes in different stages, like think about memory.
So here actually we considered we have two different memory instruction, memory and data memory.
But if you have only one memory, then when you're fetching, you cannot write to that memory, for
example, right?
Or you cannot read from memory.
For a load word instruction, you need to load the from that memory, but another instruction also
need to be fetched from that memory.
So that memory is actually kind of a resource contention, which we consider that there is no there
because we have two memories.
There are also other resource contention that you can think of.
We're going to see actually one example very soon.
But essentially for resource contention, if you are rich enough you can just increase your resources
but that would come at the price of essentially higher area power consumption and also higher cost.
Also how to handle long latency multi cycle operations for memory?
Instruction, for example, you have long latency, how we can handle exception and interrupts, which
going to be actually the topic for the next week on Thursday.
For example, when you're executing your instruction, you have division by zero.
So how are we going to handle it?
So that's going to be the topic for the late and how are we going to improve pipeline throughput,
essentially how to minimise the stalls, OK.
So I think it's a perfect place to stop.
Let's be back at 3:15 and we will continue with this topic.
OK, let's continue.
So we so there are different 'cause that provide makes the pipeline to stall and we kind of into
define the stall actually in the before the break.
But more formally start is a condition when the pipeline stops moving.
And there are different reason like resource contention dependences and long latency operations.
These are called the dependency.
Also, your book actually call it hazard, which is which.
We don't like that terminology much because in the end hazard is so alarming, you know, terminology.
In the end, these are dependencies and in order to do a good work, in order to do a good reasonable,
let's say operation, you have some dependencies in the end.
So you need to just understand the dependencies and you know, design your pipeline to deal with them
nicely.
Also, resource contention is sometimes called resource dependence as well, which but this is this
resource contention is not fundamental to the to the programmer in the end.
So it's not fun dictated by program semantics.
Whereas the data dependence and control dependence are actually dictated by the program semantics.
So that's why we'll treat resource contention separately.
And in fact, we're going to start with that first.
So this happens when instructions in two pipeline stages need the same resource.
SO1 solution is that we just eliminate the cause of contention.
So we duplicate the resource or increase the throughput of that.
So remember in laundry machine for example, we just in laundry load, we just increase the number of
dryers.
One example would be we use separate instruction and data memory, which we already done caches
you're going to see later in later lectures.
Another example is that we can use multiple ports for memory structures.
So you can have multiple read ports, multiple write ports for your memory structure in order to do
that.
Another solution is that we detect the resource contention and then install one of the contending
stages.
So that's the way you need to handle it.
If you don't, if you only care about the correctness in the end.
So just detect it and you need to stall the one of them that they are contending for the for that
stage.
Then actually the question is that which which stage do you install?
And So what if you had a single read and write port for the register file?
So here is actually an example for your book.
That's you.
So this instruction load word here when it finishes, when it wants to do the write back at cycle 5.
There is another instruction here that needs to that's needs to read some registers from the
register file here.
So if your register file for example has only one read and write port or for example, if your
register file, if you're if you need to load the same register, right In this example, actually
you're not loading the same register for this instruction.
So this is T5 and T6, while in this load word you're writing to S2.
So in that sense, actually you can have a this with a careful design of the register file, you can
be you should be able to write in the first half of cycle and then read from the register file in
the second-half of your your cycle.
So your cycle time is long enough which accommodate for writing in the first half of cycle and then
you can read for the second-half.
So how you can implement it fully in the in the register file?
This kind of abstraction for for us now I mean in this in this course, but it's possible.
So you can, you can write, write takes place during the first half of the cycle and then reads takes
place during the second-half of the cycle, which causes no problem for us.
So with that, you can actually handle this read and write from or to the register file that has only
half a clock cycle to complete.
So if you consider that you can essentially handle this resource contention, that might be the case
in register file.
So you hear you write in the first half and then you read from the register file in the second-half
of the cycle.
We're going to see that.
We call it actually as a kind of a internal register file for wording.
We're going to see it see it later as well.
So there are different data dependencies.
Now we're going to see a lot in.
Data dependencies and some of them are actually flow dependence which we call it true data
dependence which is read after write.
Essentially there are some instructions that they are producing some value and then you need to
consume these values and that's a data dependence that you need to deal with it even in a control
flow design.
Remember that in in data flow, in data flow design, which actually you relax a lot of dependencies,
but there is this dependency that you you still need to care when you design that that of low
machine.
You essentially you have this producer and consumer model in most of the applications which you need
to take care of it.
There are also some other dependencies like anti dependence which writing after read we're going to
see with example and also output dependence that you write after write.
So basically for all of them, we need to ensure semantics of the program is correct.
And also flow dependences always need to be obeyed because they constitute true dependence on a
value.
However, this anti and output dependence they are actually exist due to the limited number of
architecture registers we're going to see with the example there later as well.
So in the end these anti and output dependencies are they are dependence on a name, not a value,
just the register name that you have and we will see how we can deal with it actually later in our
other voter execution.
But in this example actually you can see these pictorially.
So in flow dependence you here you're reading from register tree when you want to actually update it
in the previous instruction.
So that's read after write or flow data dependence, anti dependence here you're writing to register
one, but register 1 needs to be read in the previous instruction.
So in a in a pipeline design, A careful pipeline design that you make sure that you always update
your registers like the write backstage is always at the last stages of the pipeline.
This anti dependence is not going to cause any problem essentially because you're going to write to
this R1 at the very, very late at the last stage.
So when when the previous instruction is to read from R1, then is actually reading from the from the
correct value.
So there is no dependency.
But if you are not careful in your design, you might actually 'cause this problem that you are in
your pipeline, you are up, you update R1 before this instruction reads from R1.
And that is actually right after read, which actually kind of again, I want to say that it's
actually a false dependency because in the end, you could easily just use a different number, a
different Register here.
So this R1 here could be R thousand, for example.
Or when you want to write to R1 here, you could write to something else.
You could have a different register number but since the number of registers are limited in our
register flight then at some point you might get to these of dependencies anti dependence and also
similarly output output dependence.
So here also it might be the the fact that these are three essentially in the end, after executing
this instruction, this R3 should really have the value of R6 operated on R7, right?
This is the latest instruction that you have.
But if you're not careful in your pipeline design, you might end up having this R1 operated on R2 as
the late last value of R3, which is clearly wrong.
OK, so, but again, this also output dependence is just because we are using the same register in
order to you know, for these two instructions, but we could just use another register.
So these are these are kind of a not not real dependences, which you can easily actually by just
changing the register value.
If you can, you can just get out of it.
OK, But this read after write is a true dependence which you really cannot do anything without it.
So that's that's why this dependence is actually very fundamental.
You produce and you want to consume it.
OK, any question, we're going to get to this right after read and right after write a lot in our
later lectures in out of order design, but just to know the concept here is also important.
Yes, here we show these instructions.
No, no, no, the, the the top instruction is the earliest instruction.
Yeah, Yeah, Now it's clear.
OK, let's continue.
So in our example we see this load word and subtract.
For example.
But what if actually, yeah, so just think about it that this subtract could have been actually a
different Register here.
So this dollar 10, if you in the in your subtract also needs to read from register 10, then you have
this data read after write dependency in your execution.
OK, so we're going to see a lot how to handle data dependence.
And you can actually also check your book.
And in addition to that, I would also recommend you check this beautiful paper, the micro
architecture of Super scalar processor, which we're going to actually use the concept a lot in more
advanced pipelining, intro and exception handling and out of order and super scalar.
So these are going to be actually the topics for the later lectures, But I think it's good thing to
start reading this beautiful paper as well.
OK, so how to handle data dependence?
So anti and output dependences are easier to handle.
We just write to the destination only in the last stage and in program order.
OK, so in our pipeline, what we already designed, if you make sure that we write to the destination
only in last stage, then we're going to get rid of this anti and output dependencies.
However, for flow dependencies, they are much more interesting, let's say, and challenging.
So there are 6 fundamental ways of handling these flow dependences, and I'm going over these
fundamental ways very, very quickly.
But we're going to see that actually in later lectures as well, some of them.
So one way is actually you just detect and wait.
So you detect the dependency and then you wait, meaning that you stole the pipeline until your
dependency is resolved.
Another way is that we detect and then we try to forward and bypass data to dependent instruction.
We're going to see a lot about it today, how we we're going to create some forwarding passes in
order to provide the data for this earlier stages.
Another way is that we detect and eliminate the dependence at the software level.
So this can be actually very powerful technique.
If you can do it, your compiler can see that there are different instructions back-to-back that they
are dependent.
So if possible compiler can try to put some independent instructions in between such that you the
compiler increase the distance between dependent instructions and that can essentially provide
performance for us.
So, but of course it depends on how effectively compiler can do it.
Yes.
Would we just then have to give some information about the?
Yes, exactly.
So you're then actually you're ISA information is to actually provide some information about your
pipeline design.
So ISA needs to actually communicate some information to the compiler essentially that the micro
architecture pipeline for example has these number of stages and then compiler needs to be aware of
that essentially.
So then some of this, the way that we defined ISA, actually there might be some now for this kind of
implementation you might need to inform, you know, some of this information to the higher level.
Yes.
Any other question?
Good.
Another fundamental way is that we detect and move it out of the way for independent instructions.
Another way would be that we predict the needed value and for example, we whenever we are dependent,
we just predict that, OK, my value is going to be 0, for example, you know, and then you continue
the execution based on that.
Your prediction is speculatively because you're, you're speculatively executing and then you need to
verify if you're if you have done a correct job, then all good.
But if wrong, you need to essentially roll back to the before your speculation execution happened.
And another interesting way is actually do something else, which is actually the concept of fine
grain multi trading, which has been used a lot, for example in GPS.
Now we're going to see that hopefully in our GPU lectures as well that whenever.
So you have thousands of threads and these threads they have different instructions.
So once one thread have you have dependency among the instructions of that, you hopefully you have
some other threads that you can just schedule instructions from other threads and that can
potentially actually keep your pipeline full using different threads, which likely you don't have
dependency between instructions of different threats essentially.
So that's the topic we're going to get to that later.
And all these actually fundamental ways actually generate a lot of basically creative ideas through
these many years that people develop for handling data dependencies.
OK, so read after write dependency.
Is actually very important.
And so here in this picture, picture also you can see that.
So when we want to write back and then this instruction is to read this register, then we have this
problem.
Even this instruction also we have this problem.
Even this instruction also we have the problem.
Only this instruction we might be able to just read.
You know, if you consider that we have this that example that we write to the register file at the
first half of the cycle and then we can read from that the second-half, then this instruction is
not dependent.
But other than that, all these instructions are dependent.
OK, so one way actually is to resolve data dependencies that we stole the pipeline.
So instruction I here is writing something to register RX and then instruction J needs to read from
this register RX, right?
So that's why when here in this instruction in the the write back essentially instruction J cannot
continue moving.
So you need to install it.
And then so that basically we just put bubbles in the pipeline.
So this instruction will wait.
Here I'm going to show you how we can kind of implement it in the micro architecture.
But pictorially also you just this instruction is to wait in the instruction fetch and then you just
move bubbles in your pipeline.
So these are bubbles until you get to this position that you can continue decoding your instruction.
OK.
So clearly when you have this data dependence, your pipeline is getting your performance, your
throughput of the pipeline is getting actually affected because you cannot keep your pipeline full
by doing useful things like you're when you're actually moving bubbles, like depending on how you
implement bubbles, in the end you are doing something, but that's something is just no pressure,
OK?
So you're not really doing useful works when you're starting, OK?
So whenever we want to install, basically we make the dependent instruction wait.
So this instruction is to wait until it's source data value is available.
So how we implement it, essentially we stop all upper stream stages, upper stream stages.
Like for example, when this instruction is waiting the decoder stage, we just stop at the fetcher
stage, OK?
And we drain all downstream stages.
So those stage downstream stages that they were doing some useful thing, they need to drain until we
get to this instruction.
Like we have this value of this write back for this instruction to continue.
And that's the way we implemented, I'm going to show you in the micro architecture also very soon.
And this is the concept of interlocking, which is detection of dependence between instructions in a
pipeline processor to guarantee correct execution.
And it can be actually software based interlocking or hardware based interlocking.
And so in software based, essentially the programmer, the compiler needs to understand these
dependency and then compiler can try to as I said put some instructions independent instruction in
between.
And if the compiler cannot find independent instructions then it needs to put some no operation.
So there might be some some ISA instruction called NO, NOP, NOP.
And then just compile it to these instruction in between just to make sure that we are resolving
dependency.
So if you have too many of these knobs, then of course your throughput is just limited because
you're not really doing useful things.
And in hardware based interlocking essentially you you need to detect it and install the pipeline.
And then there are different ways how we can improve the performance which we're going to see that.
Does anyone knows the what MIPS acronym is like MIPS stands for what?
Because actually we use MIPS a lot, but we never talk about it.
Yes, MEGA instructions per second.
No, it's not that actually.
Hopefully yeah, that would be good.
Actually MIPS if if provide million millions of instruction per second, but it's not that anyone M
stands for micro architecture and I stands for interlocking.
So actually MIPS stands for something like micro architecture without interlocked pipeline stages,
something like that.
Basically when people were designing MIPS ISA, they wanted, they had this idea that they wanted to
have a micro architecture that which doesn't have any hardware based interlocking.
So everything should be handled at the compiler.
Well, that didn't really work out well.
And in later editions of the MIPS, they actually have it heavy implementation of hardware based
interlocking and in the end you can actually use both of them together.
So it's not decision of either this or that essentially.
OK, that's for fun.
So we have a different approaches to detect dependency in the in the hardware.
So one of them is a scoreboarding.
We're going to see a scoreboarding also a lot in the out of order execution.
So scoreboarding essentially is actually quite easy.
Like each register in register 5 has a valid bit associated with it.
An instruction that is writing to the register resets the valid bit.
So once you're decoding an instruction and you know that this instruction needs to write to, for
example, register 2, then you need to reset the valid bit of register 2, basically telling later
instructions that this register to value is obsolete.
So you need to wait for a valid information.
So that's the idea here.
And an instruction in the decode stage, basically you check if all its source and destination
registers are valid and if all of them are valid, then you can basically keep going.
So no need to install, there's no dependence.
If no, you need to install the instruction essentially.
So that's the one way to implement this idea.
So advantage is that it's actually quite simple because you add only one bit per register.
However, disadvantage is that we need to install for all types of self dependencies, not only flow
dependency.
And why is that?
Because you here you actually check both source and destination registers.
So you even you install for read after write.
I'm sorry for write after read and write after write dependencies.
OK, so that's a scoreboarding.
Yeah.
So here for example, this subtract instruction because it you need to for example, read from
register 10, then you can actually install it using this scoreboard.
OK, another way which your book also assume that is having this combination of dependence check
logic.
So essentially you need to have a combinational circuits that basically you need to get the
information for later stages.
So whenever you are at the decoded stage, you you know that these are the registers that you want to
read.
And then with your, this combinational circuit gets input from later stages as well.
And you know that you can see that if there is a equality between the registers that you want to
read and registers that they are touched that they're going to be touched by the later stages.
So if there is some equality, then you see that OK, I need to wait essentially.
And if there is no equality, then OK, there is no dependence and you can keep going, OK.
So I think by your understanding of how to implement combinational circuits, I think it's actually
very easy to implement.
So I'm not going to go over it very in too much detail.
But essentially if the you see that there is some equality between your, essentially your registers
that you want to read, you need to install the instructional pipeline.
If no, you just continue executing.
So the advantage here is that there is no need to install on anti and output dependencies here.
So which is good, but there are a lot of disadvantage here that logic is more complex than a
scoreboard and the logic becomes more complex as we make the pipeline deeper.
So in our here example, our pipeline is 5 stages, but what will happen if your pipeline has 20
stages?
OK, So then actually you need to get input from all these stages in order to see if there is a
dependency or not.
Whereas in other way scoreboarding, you just check one bit.
OK?
So that's the trade off essentially here And here also say that flash forward, which is superscalar
execution, we're going to see that actually, I don't know, in maybe 3 or 4 later lectures in super
scaler, actually you might have you, you, you're going to duplicate your pipeline, several
pipelines.
So you're going to have several pipelines and then you need to actually also check all of them as
well in this kind of dependency logic.
But you're going to get to that later.
OK, so, so once we detect the dependence in the hardware, then what do you do afterwards?
So essentially now we have one option which is to stall the dependent instruction right away.
And the second option is that we can stall the dependent instruction only when necessary.
So, so the first option is actually just ensure the correctness, but essentially it doesn't it's not
good for performance reasons.
And the second option is try to make sure that we are correct and high performance, which we're
going to also see ways for that.
There are also other options which we don't get to it.
In this lecture, but we're going to see that hopefully later.
So that's a topic of data for wording and bypassing.
So that's the problem that the consumer instruction has to wait in the decoder stage until the
producer instruction writes its value in the register part.
OK, so we discuss about it.
So now the goal is that we do not want to install the pipeline unnecessarily.
So how we do it, essentially the idea is that the data value needed by the consumer instruction can
be supplied directly from a later stage in the pipeline instead of only from the register file.
So once that, for example, your ALU generates the the value that you need to for your execution, you
can just bypass it.
You don't need to wait to read it from the register file.
So that's the idea here that essentially we add additional dependence check logic and data
forwarding pass or buses to supply the producers value to the consumer right after the value is
available, which is actually very similar how we do it actually in real in that of low machine,
right.
So whenever the data is ready, you just pass it and you can fire instructions.
So here is also the case when when the data is ready and we can continue executing, we try to do it.
We don't wait for that.
So that's provide essentially benefit that you have less stalling essentially in the end.
So now let's see how we can implement both stalling logic and how we can add this forwarding passes
essentially.
So when you want to, for example, stall here, you essentially disable program counter, make sure
that you don't change the program counter.
And also you disable instruction fetch and instruction decode thatching.
So this also is not going to be changed.
OK, so that's the one this ensure stall instruction stays in its stage.
So that's the way we implement and also we insert invalid instruction or no operations into the
stage following the start one called bubbles.
So here for example other stage we just push bubbles.
So how you can implement it?
Well, there are different ways to implement bubbles.
One way would be just, you know, just clear up all these registers, all zeros and all control
signals like those important control signal like right enables or whatever, those are all zeros
such that you make sure you don't cause harm.
OK.
But you can also think of some other ways also, you know that when you're studying, you can
potentially try to clock it, you know, some of these stages to save also power as well.
But these are not in the end not very important for the for understanding of this lecture.
You just need to make sure that you don't harm to other stages.
So there are multiple different ways of implementing it.
OK, so here is an example.
So how we can handle it.
This read off, read off the right data dependent example.
So there is this instruction that you're going to write to this register is 0.
And then there is another instruction here and that you need to read from this register.
So it's a kind of exactly this one produce and this one is going to consume OK.
So clearly you cannot continue like that.
So you need to essentially.
So this is going to read wrong value.
If you just continue like that, this instruction is going to also read wrong value.
And only this instruction, if you consider that internal forwarding pass, which we discussed in the
register for it can read the correct value.
So that's why we need to essentially stall and push bubbles in the execution.
So that's the way.
So in the at the compile time, you can actually add no operations.
You know, between this addition and then the dependent instruction, which is the next one, you can
just add Nope.
And that can fix the problem.
Of course, now your compiler needs to be aware of the micro architecture.
There should be some information about the pipeline stages such that compiler can handle it.
But the problem is that adding this no operation is not free.
Like when you add them you have useless instructions OK which going to cause performance overhead.
So ideally compile time need to under find some instructions that they are independent and can use
them as an operation essentially.
So you are you're going to use, you're going to do useful works while you're resolving your
dependence.
So essentially compiler is trying to reorder, reschedule and insert instruction at the compiler
level in order to fix this problem.
So in data forwarding which is also called data passing data bypassing in the hardware.
So you forward the result value to the dependent instruction as soon as the value is available and
which we have already seen this basic idea in data flow machine that we can do that and with data
forwarding actually you can see that now the micro.
Is getting closer to the to the data flow execution model or principles that we have seen.
OK, so how we can do that?
So this instruction which going to produce the value of this register S 0 is going to be the data is
going to be available at this stage, OK, because this ALU I calculate this addition and then this
value is actually available here.
So you can just clearly just put the forward from this state to the to the input of the ALU.
So from this, this clear nice forwarding pass and essentially you should also have some multiplexer
here in order to make sure that you select from the forwarding pass and not from this register.
OK?
But assuming that you're doing that, you can just forward and data from this stage to this stage and
then this instruction can get going.
And also this value is also ready.
I mean, this is generated here, so it's ready here.
And also you pass it to the next stage as well because you want to do it right back here, right?
So this value, this new register is also available here.
You can also have another bypassing pass from from the memory stage to the beginning of the executed
stage essentially.
So with that also you can do that.
So essentially we can do from latched output of ALU to the input of ALU.
That's one for wording pass.
Another would be from right back to input of ALU and from right back to the register file which we
have already seen that which we call it.
It is actually internal for avoiding pass in the register file OK.
Questo è OK.
Yeah.
So we have these different forwarding pass here actually also shown in this micro architecture.
So this red one is actually from latch output of ALU to the input of ALU.
And you need to do it for two sources because you don't know this is going to be consumed for which
sources of the Lu.
So you need to provide in both.
And also this yellow forwarding pass is actually from the right back to the input of ALU, OK?
And then from register file, you assume that your register file can handle it, that you can write in
the first half and then read from the second-half of your cycle.
OK, so that's forwarding.
So we forward to execute the stage from either memory stage or write back stage.
And now the question is that when should we forward from either memory or write back stage?
Like if that decision we write to a destination register and the destination register matches the
source register.
So that's our logic to understand that we need to use the forwarding pass.
And then another question is that if both the memory and write back stages contain matching
destination register, then which one you're going to protise?
So if both of them actually are matching the same register, so which one you're going to protise?
So of course, we're going to protise this red line because this actually has the more recent value
from the from the younger instruction essentially.
So that's the way you can protise in order to make sure that you forward the right value to the
execute Your book actually also provide this pseudo code, you know, to understand it better how we
can implement this forwarding logic.
So I let you go over it at home if you're interested And but the problem is that data forwarding is
not always possible.
So think about load word instruction.
So load word instruction essentially you, you have the value that you want to write the 0 actually
at the end of the memory stage, OK, you can potentially think about forwarding end of the memory
stage to the beginning of your ALU stage.
OK, so that's kind is possible.
But the problem is that if you do that, then your critical pass latency is increasing.
So now the your clock cycle needs to handle the memory stage and also the executed stage because you
need to, you need to be sure that these combinational circuit is going to fit in your clock cycle.
So that's why if you don't, it's better to not do that, of course.
And also assuming that memory stage is very slow and can be very slow, people don't do that most of
the time.
So that's why we don't provide this forwarding pass.
And then essentially this instruction whenever we have load word as the earlier instruction, you
need to you need to stop.
So this instruction and here you need to install at least for one for one cycle here in our example
and then it can continue to the for the execution.
OK, So with our with our forwarding pass, we kind of fix all the data dependence unless we have this
load word instruction.
So with load word, the next instruction if it is dependent needs to wait at least for one second.
Yes, yes, it's a tough task to do of course.
And then you need to test it.
What you have done was correct or not, but yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's why we are paying a lot also for to buy these chips, OK.
But these are costs that they are hopefully only one, one time.
I mean, after you change the processor, you need to spend a lot, but you you spend that time to
generate and a lot of cost.
And then hopefully you're going to, you know, sell thousand of that chips or millions of that chips.
OK, so yeah, this is the picture how we handle stalling independence.
So you essentially you disable program counter and also disable this fetch, decode register and all
of them you basically you book said that we flush them or clear them.
Essentially you write 0 such that you make sure that you don't harm in later stages of the pipeline.
OK, so this is the hardware and that we need to support for stalls so we have this.
Enable inputs to the to the fetch and decode pipeline registers and also we have synchronous reset
or clear input to the execute pipeline registers when we want to stop.
It can be in different ways of implementation as well.
However, when a load word stall occurs we we need to keep the values in the decode and fetch a stage
pipeline register as well.
OK.
So these are just a summary of what we have discussed for you to check later question.
I think we have time to cover this control dependence as well, at least some part of it and then
we'll see.
So there's a special case of data dependence, which is control dependence.
Is it kind of a data dependence on the instruction pointer or program counter?
OK, so control dependence, the question is that what should the fetch PC be in the next cycle?
So the simple answer is that it's going to be the address of the next instruction, OK.
But then the problem is that how can we know the address of the next instruction?
So if the fetch instruction is a non control flow instruction, next fetch PC is the address of the
next sequential instruction which is in MIPS for example.
It's going to be PC +4 OK, which is easy to determine if we know the size of the fetch instruction,
which is the case for MIPS ISA for example.
However, if the instruction that is fetch is a control flow instruction like branch or jump, then
how do we determine the next fetch PC?
And in fact, how do we know whether or not the fetch instruction is a control flow or not?
So you know it after you decode it, right?
At the fetch of stage, you have no idea if you do, if you're fetching branch or not.
OK.
So that's the concept of branch prediction, which is a special case of data dependence, which is
your dependence on the program counter.
You try to predict that you have branch and whether or not you're going to take take the pass or not
take the pass.
So in branch, if we call conditional branch, branch is not resolved until the 4th stage of the
pipeline.
OK, you need to do it at the fourth stage.
Instructions after the branch are fetched before the branch is resolved.
And that's can cause the problem essentially, right?
So we can have a simple branch prediction example that we always predict that the next sequential
instruction is fetch, which is called always not taken prediction.
So whenever you have instruction, you don't care if it's a branch or not, you just fetch the PC +4.
And this is a kind of a prediction essentially, right?
You predict that I'm not going to take any of the branches.
OK, We're going to see a more let's say intelligent branch prediction also later in this course.
And then after we resolve the branch, we need to flush or invalidate non taken pass instruction if
the branch is taken.
OK, so you there is a branch instruction you don't know if you're going to take or not, so you just
keep fetching other instructions.
But once you resolve that branch instructions is taken, then you need to flush those wrong
instructions that you have fetched, which going to be, you know, you need to pay that as a plant
penalty of the pipeline because your pipeline is going to be empty.
And then you need to wait until you have it full and get to the steady state.
And that's actually one of the reason that people should be careful about the stages of the
pipeline.
When your pipeline is deep, then you're going to pay much more for these branch instructions
essentially.
OK, so that's branch miss prediction penalty that people need to pay a number of instructions
flushed when branch is incorrectly predicted.
So this penalty can be reduced by resolving the branch earlier, which we call it early branch
resolution.
So how we do it?
This is our pipeline so far, but design so and this is actually the the example that we discussed
about it, the control how we flush and miss prediction.
So here is a branch.
If you call and then you actually you have some instructions in your pipeline which you miss because
of the miss prediction, you are actually executing them.
So you need to flush all of these instructions.
You flush these instructions and then you continue feeding your pipeline from the right pass.
So that's the way.
So in order to reduce this overhead, you can calculate branch target and condition in the decoder
stage.
So that's the early branch resolution.
So you add this equality check, you'd add this equality check here in the decoder stage.
And so with that, you can actually decide on your branch whether or not you want to take or not at
the decoder stage.
OK.
So if that's the case, you also need to move this logic for calculating the target address as well.
So this is the condition check and this is the logic for the target address.
So all of them you need to put.
In the decoder stage such that you can resolve the branch early enough.
So if you do that then you only need to flush this instruction.
OK other instruction you basically you don't fetch them because you are now resolving branch quite
early.
So early branch resolution is a good idea.
So of course, it has advantages like reduce branch miss prediction penalty and that reduced CPI for
you, but has disadvantage because that potentially increasing the clock cycle time because now
you're decoded stage, you're doing more work.
So it can potentially increase your clock cycle time.
So in the end, whether or not you need to, whether or not it's a good idea or not, you need to
evaluate it, OK?
And this also adds additional hardware costs, as you can see.
So in the end, we need to get to this performance analysis basic.
So we are reducing CPI, but we are increasing clock cycle time.
So in the end, it might be useful or not.
So we should see.
But that's not the old thing.
Actually your branch might be your BEQ instruction might need registers that they're going to be
produced actually by earlier instructions.
So you also need to, if you want to do it correctly, you need to add forwarding pass for these
decoded station.
So now you also need to forward from the from the memory after the ALU latched ALU, and also from
potentially from the output of the memory to the decoded stage as well in order to resolve
branches.
Again, whether or not it's a good idea, you need to evaluate it because this adds some complexity,
some longer latency, and can potentially cause longer clock cycle time.
OK.
So here also some from your book like how we can handle forwarding and studying the hardware
control.
You can think of this like a very long implementation of it, so you can check it.
And this actually our final pipeline needs processor from H&H which has includes always not taken
branch prediction, early branch resolution and forwarding and install logic.
So you can go over it with for more detail later.
OK, but we can do better.
Of course for branch prediction, they can, they can be much smarter.
You can have different idea.
So for example, you know that backward branches, usually they are used to implement loops and you
know that for loops you're going to take the branch most of the time.
So you can use this idea in order to have better prediction for branches.
You can actually also keep history of your branches and based on the history that you keep, decide
whether or not you want to take or not take these branches.
So accurate branch prediction reduces the fraction of branches that requires a flush.
So that's why this is actually this been, it's been a topic for many years and it's still also in
top computer architecture conferences that people try to come up with a better algorithms to
predict branches.
It can be actually much more sophisticated.
For example, you can use machine learning technique for that, but we're going to see in our branch
prediction lecture, if you are impatient, you can actually also check some earlier lectures on
that, but we're going to see later as well.
So I will stop here.
The rest of this lecture, we have some example on performance of the pipeline, which I leave it
actually to you.
You can actually go over on these slides, provide some example.
And next week, we're going to start with the next topic, which is I guess precise exception.
So have a nice weekend and see you all next week.